Guide to the William Inglis Morse Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Inglis Morse collection
1710-1947
MS 1192
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3
(1 box, 1 folio)
The collection consists of autograph letters, business papers, and legal papers, in French and English, almost all to or by Canadians. The papers also contain an account book of Morse's transactions with the Yale Art Library and correspondence relating to the Howe family of Nova Scotia, chiefly Joseph Howe's duel with John Croke Halliburton.
Morse, William Inglis, 1874-1952
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William Inglis Morse, 1946.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
William Inglis Morse was born in Paradise, Nova Scotia, on June 4, 1874. He graduated from Acadia College in 1897 and the Episcopal Theological School in 1900. Morse preached in Connecticut and Massachusetts until 1929 and then devoted himself to historical research. He collected maps, books, and manuscripts relating to Nova Scotia and Canada. Morse died in Cambridge, Massachusetts, on June 4, 1952.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of autograph letters, business papers, and legal papers, in French and English, almost all to or by Canadians. The papers also contain an account book of Morse's transactions with the Yale Art Library and correspondence relating to the Howe family of Nova Scotia, chiefly Joseph Howe's duel with John Croke Halliburton.
Dueling -- Canada; Families; Canada -- History; Account books; Autographs; Austin, Joseph; Bell, Robert, 1845-1926; Bouchette, Errol, 1863-1912; Bourinot, John George, 1837-1902; Brymner, Douglas, 1823-1902; Call, Frank Oliver, 1876-; Cannon, Lawrence A. D.; Cathcart, Charles Murray, 2nd Earl of.; Colden, Cadwallader, 1688-1776; Curwood, James Oliver, 1878-1927; David, L.-O. (Laurent-Olivier), 1840-1926; Dawson, John William, Sir, 1820-1899; Denault, Laure B.; Doyle, Charles Hastings; Elgin, James Bruce, Earl of, 1811-1863; Fitzpatrick, Charles, Sir, 1853-; Foster, George Eulas, Sir, 1847-; Gerard, John, 1840-1912; Gordon, John Campbell, 7th Earl of Aberdeen; Gordonsmith, Charles R.W.; Halliburton, John Croke; Henry, William Alexander; Howe, Joseph, 1804-1873; Hunter-Duvar, John, 1821-1899; Kennedy, Howard Angus, 1861-1938; Laurier, Wilfrid, Sir, 1841-1919; Le Moyne de Longueuil, Joseph Dominique Emanuel, 1738-1807; Le Rossignol, James Edward, 1866-1959; Lizars, Kathleen Macfarlane; McLean, Archibald W.; McLeod, Margaret Arnett, 1877-; Montgomery, L. M. (Lucy Maud), 1874-1942; Morison, Bryce; Morse, William Inglis, 1874-1952; Muirhead, James F. (James Fullarton), 1853-1934; Myrand, Ernest, 1854-; O'Sullivan, Michael; Robison, John, 1739-1805; Roy, Camille, 1870-1943; Scott, Henry Arthur, 1858-1931; Smith, J. Allen (James Allen), 1860-1926; Stobo, Robert, 1726-1770; Struan, Alexander Robertson, 13th baron; Tuthill, Zechariah; Wolfe, James, 1727-1759; Wood, William, 1864-1947; Young, George R. (George Renny), 1802-1853; Howe family; Yale University -- Libraries
- Inventory
  - Autograph letters
    - Tuthill, Zechariah, 1710 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Struan, Alexander Robertson, 13th baron, 1716 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Colden, Cadwallader, 1762 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Hoyle, James, 1792 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - De Longueuil, Joseph D.E., 1805 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Greenock, Charles Murray Cathcart, called Lord, 1815 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Cathcart, Charles Murray Cathcart, 2nd Earl of, 1816 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Gillespie Gerrand & Co., 1817 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Emmet & Selden, 1823 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Jenkins, Seth, 1823 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Ashton, Thomas, 1828 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Mackie, Lockhart & Co., 1828 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Tappan & Mansfield, 1829 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - [Cazeau, C.F.?], 1830 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Blackburn, George & Robert, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Elgin, James Bruce, 8th Earl of, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Dawson, Sir John W., 1880 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Brymner, Douglas, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Deville, Edouard Gaston, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bell, Robert, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bourinot, Sir John George, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - [Rosny?], E., 1890 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Hunter-Duvar, John, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Muirhead, James F., 1893 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Myrand, Ernest, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Lizárs, Kathleen M., 1898 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Scott, Henry A., 1902 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Le Rossignol, James Edward, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bryce, Morison, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Gerund, John, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Aberdeen and Temair, Sir John Campbell Gordon, 7th Earl of, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - David, Laurent Olivier, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - D_______, Errol, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Bryce, Morison, 1908-1913 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Cannon, Lawrence Arthur Dumoulin, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Fitzpatrick, Charles, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Aberdeen and Temair, Sir John Campbell Gordon, 7th Earl of, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Laurier, Sir Wilfred, 1913, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Roy, Camille, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Roy, Camille, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Aucoin, Dr. E.-D., 1921 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Kennedy, Howard A., 1925 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Foster, George G., 1925 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Curwood, James Oliver, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Descarries, A_______, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Call, Frank Oliver, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Watson, William R., 1933 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Macleod, Margaret, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Denault, Laure B., 1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Macdonald, Lucy Maud (Montgomery), 1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Pacifique de Valigny, Rev. Père, [1939] (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Autograph business and legal papers, 1771-1895 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Howe family of Nova Scotia
    - Correspondence, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1840 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1847, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, 1869-1887 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Photographs of documents, letters and other manuscripts, as well as pictures and maps in the William I. Morse Papers (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Photostat of the index to the manuscripts of M. le Chevalier de Levis, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - List of Canadian books not in the Yale Library donated by William I. Morse, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Sales book of flour; Branding book, with sales of flour, 1855-1875 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Canadian documents, 1778, 1833-38 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - French Canadian documents, 1738-56 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Photograph of H.R.H. Edward, Prince of Wales, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Photostat of an ALS by Charles Lawrence, with dealer's letter and transcript, 1755, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Will of Thomas Phillips, 1842 (Box 2)
  - Deed of Samuel Wilson, 1865 (Box 2)
  - Membership certificate of W. Gardner, 1869 (Box 2)